Shri Mataji: Just help him, one person can’t do it, somebody else.
Shri Mataji: Aiutalo, una persona sola non può farcela, qualcun altro.
Marcus, Nick, anyone, just help him out,
Marcus, Nick, chiunque, aiutatelo,
What’s there?
Cosa c’è là?
Alan, go and tell Bai to bring My handkerchief from My...
Alan, vai a dire a Bai di portarmi il mio fazzoletto che è nella mia…
I’ve got My pur- No, no, it’s all right, it’s here,
ho la mia… no, no, va bene, è qui, l’avete portato insieme alla borsa? Sì, è qui.
Man: Here’s Your purse, Mother.
Yogi: Ecco la Sua borsa, Madre.
Shri Mataji: Have the Americans come, those who have done the Puja, have they come?
Shri Mataji: Sono arrivati gli americani, quelli che hanno fatto il puja?
Shri Mataji: Oh, they are here. Then it’s all right.
Shri Mataji: Oh, sono qui. Allora va bene.
And, in these new centers,
E in questi nuovi centri
have you started with Puja anywhere? Sahaja Yogini: Yes, Mother.
avete iniziato i puja da qualche parte? Sahaja yogini: Sì, Madre.
Shri Mataji: No, yours is all right, I’m asking about England.
Shri Mataji: No, il tuo (centro) è a posto, sto chiedendo dell’Inghilterra.
Warren: Any centres in Britain? Where there are new people.
Warren: Qualche centro in Gran Bretagna, dove ci sono persone nuove?
Shri Mataji: Cheltenham, for example. Where is Alan? Ask him.
Shri Mataji: Cheltenham, per esempio. Dov’è Alan? Chiedeteglielo.
Warren: He’s just gone out for a moment. Any centers in Britain,
Warren: È uscito un attimo. Ci sono adesso qui
any new people here, right now?
persone nuove da qualche centro britannico?
Shri Mataji: If do you have introduced them to puja I don’t mind,
Shri Mataji: Se li avete introdotti al puja non mi preoccupo,
but if they have never been introduced to puja, then you have to be careful.
ma se non sono mai stati iniziati al puja dovete stare attenti.
From their good point of view.
Per il loro bene.
I’m sorry I had to say this,
Mi dispiace aver dovuto dire questo,
because yesterday the load was too much, you know I couldn’t speak even,
ma ieri il peso è stato troppo, sapete, non riuscivo neppure a parlare;
and lifting the Kundalini was like raising hundred donkeys on your head,
e alzare la Kundalini è stato come sollevare cento asini sulla testa,
it was too much.
è stato troppo.
And all these half-baked people are such that they are like dog-in-the-manger,
E tutta questa gente immatura è come il cane nella mangiatoia:
they won’t have it and they won’t allow others to have it.
non lo vuole e non permetterà agli altri di averlo.
They’ll argue before the program, before the meeting starts,
Discuteranno prima del programma, prima che inizi l’incontro,
before the puja starts, specially.
prima dell’inizio del puja, specialmente.
Because they don’t want you to enjoy the fruits of the puja;
Questo perché non vogliono che gioiate dei frutti del puja;
they’ll spoil your attention,
danneggeranno la vostra attenzione,
they’ll argue, discuss. [Aside: “Please sit down.”]
polemizzeranno, discuteranno. [A lato: “Siediti, per favore”.]
What is there to argue in Sahaj Yoga? You have to take, that’s the point is,
Che c’è da discutere in Sahaja Yoga? Dovete prendere, è quello il punto,
you have to take, there’s nothing to argue.
dovete ricevere, non c’è niente da discutere.
How much you take is the point.
Il punto è quanto prendete.
And the worst part is that they don’t want to grow and they want to pull you down.
E l’aspetto peggiore è che non vogliono crescere e vogliono trascinarvi in basso.
So, unless and until they are introduced to the idea of puja beforehand -
Quindi, a meno che il puja non sia stato loro spiegato in anticipo…
then they start understanding the worth of puja, otherwise they do not,
allora cominciano a capire il valore del puja. Altrimenti non (capiranno),
how will they understand? You see, it’s beyond them.
come faranno a capire? Vedete, è oltre la loro capacità di comprensione.
So, you should not make them attend any puja, minimum,
Quindi, come minimo, non dovreste farli partecipare a nessun puja
and also seminars I would say. Because seminars are meant for people
e neppure ai seminari, direi. Infatti, i seminari sono per persone
who are intensively in Sahaj Yoga, to intensify their awareness.
che si dedichino a Sahaja Yoga con intensità,
Not for people who are half-baked, who are Doubting Thomases,
e non per gente immatura che dubita come San Tommaso.
all this kind of people are absolutely useless,
Tutte queste persone sono assolutamente inutili,
you should never bring them to a seminar.
non dovreste mai portarle ad un seminario.
Whether it’s your son, father, brother, mother, sister, husband, wife,
Che si tratti di vostro figlio, padre, fratello, madre, sorella, marito, moglie,
nothing doing. You shouldn’t bring anybody who is not
niente da fare. Non dovreste portare nessuno che non sia
fully awakened Sahaja Yogi,
un sahaja yogi completamente risvegliato,
because seminars are meant for very intensive work-out.
perché i seminari servono per un lavoro molto intensivo.
And what I find, always these people will argue with Me,
E ciò che noto è che queste persone discuteranno sempre con me,
they are the first to question, they have something to say
sono le prime a fare domande, hanno (sempre) qualcosa da dire,
I don’t mind even that, but what happens in the seminar, you have to receive more.
A me non importa neppure di questo, ma ciò che accade al seminario
And they do not receive, their attention is outside, they are disturbing everyone.
Mentre loro non assorbono, la loro attenzione è all’esterno, disturbano tutti.
So, seminars are even, in a way, more important than an ashram,
Dunque, in un certo senso, i seminari sono addirittura più importanti di un ashram,
because in ashram there’s no other problem but to fight them out.
perché in ashram esiste soltanto il problema di liberarsi di certa gente.
But here, in a new place we go, we have to fight out all surroundings,
Qui invece andiamo in un posto nuovo, dobbiamo combattere
whom you have to convince. If they are not convinced, why are they here?
che dovete convincere. Se non sono convinti, perché sono qui?
Why did they spend so much money to come down?
Perché hanno speso tanto denaro per venire qui?
Be sure, they have come here to disturb us. I’m sorry we had to do that way.
State certi che sono venuti per disturbarci.
I wish people could be simple, straightforward,
Vorrei che le persone potessero essere semplici, dirette,
uncomplicated, and sensitive, but they are not.
senza complicazioni e sensibili, ma non lo sono.
They are not sensitive people. They don’t understand what are they up to.
Non sono sensibili, non capiscono cosa stanno facendo.
By that they destroy themselves, no doubt, but they destroy part of you also,
In questo modo distruggono se stesse, indubbiamente,
Such a deep subject and it was too heavy for Me.
Era un argomento molto profondo ed è stato troppo pesante per me.
If they say they feel bad, all right, tell them: “We are sorry, we can’t help you.”
Se dicono di rimanerci male, beh, rispondete:
See, there are certain points where we have to have our freedom
Vedete, ci sono alcuni punti in cui dobbiamo avere la nostra libertà
to allow those who can come in. That’s the point where we close the door.
di lasciar entrare (solo) quelli che possono entrare.
And there’s nothing wrong in it, because you have to equip more to pull them out.
E non c’è niente di sbagliato in questo,
It has been always our practice, since long, there’s nothing new about it,
È sempre stata la nostra prassi, da tanto tempo, non c’è niente di nuovo in merito;
everyone knows, not only in England, or any other place, even in India:
lo sanno tutti, non solo in Inghilterra, in qualsiasi altro posto, anche in India:
we never allowed anybody to come for the Puja who was not a realized soul,
non abbiamo mai permesso di partecipare al puja a chi non fosse un’anima realizzata
and who was not a Sahaja Yogi, from the very beginning.
e un sahaja yogi, fin dall’inizio.
Wherever we tried that, we found it was very difficult.
Ovunque abbiamo provato a farlo, lo abbiamo trovato molto difficile.
So I hope there’s nobody sitting here with a doubting mind.
Spero quindi che qui non sia presente nessuno con una mente dubbiosa.
If somebody’s there he should with all sincerity leave the hall
Se c’è qualcuno così, dovrebbe con tutta sincerità lasciare la sala
and leave us alone, for the ascent.
e non disturbarci, per l’ascesa.
Anybody who has doubts should be kind and generous about it.
Chiunque abbia dubbi dovrebbe essere gentile e generoso su questo punto.
It’s a very serious work we are doing. It’s not of making money
È un lavoro molto serio quello che stiamo facendo. Non si tratta di guadagnare denaro
or of throwing an enterprise or building a house or something like that.
o aprire un’impresa o costruire una casa o qualcosa di simile.
It’s not even just making creations of worlds,
Non consiste neppure soltanto nel creare dei mondi;
it’s much more than that, it’s a very serious work we are doing
è molto più di questo, è un lavoro molto serio quello che stiamo facendo
and we don’t want anybody to cut our attention.
e non vogliamo che nessuno distolga la nostra attenzione.
Even some of the Sahaja Yogis I know, are half-baked.
So che anche alcuni sahaja yogi sono immaturi.
They must be corrected, all right, doesn’t matter, but they have been exposed to pujas,
Devono essere corretti, va bene, non importa, ma hanno partecipato ai puja
so it will do them good, not bad.
quindi a loro farà bene, non male.
But some people are just anti-God, and they have allergies for God.
Alcune persone, però, sono proprio contro Dio
Any work you’d start doing in the name of God, they are so allergic, they react.
Qualsiasi lavoro si inizi a fare nel nome di Dio,
These are anti-God allergies,
Si tratta di allergie nei confronti di Dio
and they express themselves by different, funny methods.
e si esprimono in modi diversi, strani.
Now, all the Sahaja Yogis must know this, then you will not go too far with them.
Adesso tutti i sahaja yogi devono rendersene conto,
You will - you should discover this in anyone this allergy existing.
Dovreste scoprire se qualcuno soffre di questa allergia.
You should say: “Sorry, we have nothing to do with you”.
Dovreste dire: “Mi spiace, non abbiamo niente a che fare con te”.
So that is for the people who have to have the privilege of this worship.
Pertanto, spetta a coloro che devono avere il privilegio di questa adorazione.
Today is specially a great privilege
Oggi in particolare è un grande privilegio
because it was not so planned,
perché non era stato pianificato ma ha funzionato,
Yesterday we did lots of cleansing. Now, today tell your mind to rest for a while.
Ieri abbiamo fatto una grande pulizia.
Tell your thoughts to stop for a while, and receive, receive more of it.
Dite ai vostri pensieri di fermarsi per un po’ e assorbite, ricevete maggiormente.
Everybody has benefited by this reception but you have to receive more.
Tutti hanno beneficiato di questo assorbimento ma dovete ricevere di più.
There’s a capacity within you to receive.
In voi c’è la capacità di ricevere.
Puja, as I have told you many-a-times, is not for My benefit, by any chance,
Il puja, come vi ho detto molte volte, non è a mio vantaggio, in nessun caso,
take it from Me. I’m much better off without it.
credetemi. Io sto molto meglio senza.
Because when the enthusiastic deities start emitting vibrations
Infatti, quando le deità entusiaste cominciano ad emettere vibrazioni
with your asking - because you are saints, you see, just they are over-enthusiastic.
a seguito delle vostre richieste…
And they are sitting there, busy-bodies, you know,
E sono sedute qui, sono armeggione, sapete;
they are sitting quietly waiting for a chance, you see, to emit vibrations,
sono sedute in silenzio in attesa di un’occasione per emettere vibrazioni,
to save you, you see they want to just rush.
per salvarvi, desiderano proprio precipitarsi.
They emit so much that they lose – “Just wait, just wait”.
Ne emettono così tante che pèrdono… (Dicono:) “Aspetta, aspetta”.
They want to save you, they want to give you, they’re so anxious,
Vogliono salvarvi, vogliono darvele, sono così ansiose,
in their anxiety you see - I like it, to see the way they are anxious.
piene d’ansia, sapete. Mi piace vedere come sono ansiose.
But you don’t suck it, and I have a problem there.
Voi però non le assorbite e, a quel punto, io ho un problema.
Once they have given they don’t want to take it back.
Una volta emesse non le rivogliono indietro. Voi non le assorbite
Is directed towards you and you don’t take it; so where does it go?
Sono dirette a voi ma voi non le ricevete; e allora dove finiscono?
It hangs into My tissues, it pains Me.
Si attaccano ai miei tessuti, mi fanno male.
So, sucking should be more. Sucking should be more.
Quindi, l’assorbimento dovrebbe essere maggiore.
And just before the Puja you should say: “Mother, make me such
E proprio prima del puja dovreste dire: “Madre, fa’
that I suck more of the Divine”.
che io assorba maggiormente dal Divino”.
Just pray that, with sincerity from your heart, just say that.
Pregate così, con sincerità nel vostro cuore, dite così.
There’s another beautiful gesture I have seen, in Uzbekistan, it’s very good.
C’è un altro bellissimo gesto che ho visto in Uzbekistan, è bellissimo.
They put both the hands on their heart like this, and just press it,
Loro appoggiano entrambe le mani sul cuore, così, e le premono
bending their head, asking. See, it creates a vacuum.
piegando il capo e chiedendo. Vedete, ciò crea un vuoto.
That’s how they bow.
Si chinano così.
It’s beautiful!
È bellissimo.
That’s very nice today.
Oggi è bellissimo.
So, let the children come here.
Fate venire qui i bambini.
[Translation: “Come, sister has come, Sister has come”].
(Hindi) Vieni, (tua) sorella è arrivata, (tua) sorella è arrivata.
Now, sit there, all of you sit down, all right? Sit down now, sit down, sit down.
Ora sedetevi lì, sedetevi tutti, va bene?
Now, come along, Matthews is also coming, sit down there,
Adesso vieni, viene anche Matthews, siediti lì, siediti,
sit down, come along, let’s see, sit down. Now all the children are very sweet,
vieni avanti, vediamo, siediti. Adesso tutti i bambini sono molto dolci
and are going to sit down. Come along, sit down, sit down, nicely.
e si siederanno. Venite, sedetevi, sedetevi per bene.
[Translation: “Where is sister? Where is sister?”
Dov’è didi? Dov’è (tua) sorella? Nipotina minore: Di sopra.
All right, now, you should give Me the flowers now,
Va bene, adesso dovreste darmi i fiori
so would be better for you to have vibrations, thank you.
sarebbe meglio per voi, per ricevere le vibrazioni. Grazie.
Now, you give Me these, to Me, give Me now. Give Me. Give Me, to Mother.
Ora dammi questi; a me, dammeli adesso. Dammeli, dalli a me, a Madre.
All right, give that also. Child [indistinctly]: But you have the one.
Bene, dammi anche quello. Bambina [non chiaro]: Ma tu ne hai uno.
Shri Mataji: Also give. So thank you,
Shri Mataji: Dai anche quello. Grazie, grazie, molte grazie.
All right, so now what should we do, Pujari is this.
Bene, adesso cosa dovremmo fare? Il pujari è questo.
Just put a tikka to him. Put to everyone, not to the Pujari.
Mettigli un tikka (bindi).
Pujari: Got it.
Pujari: Ce l’ho. Shri Mataji: Bene. Bene. È kajal?
Good. May God bless you.
Bene. Dio vi benedica.
All right. Now, the children should sit like this, all right?
Bene. Adesso i bambini dovrebbero sedersi così, capito?
On the side, for Ganesha Puja, like this, straight.
Ai lati, per il puja a Ganesha, così, dritti.
So everybody can take photograph also,
In questo modo tutti possono anche scattare fotografie.
sit like this, all right? Ah. They have to take photographs. Yes, good, good.
Sedetevi così, va bene? Ah. Devono scattare fotografie. Sì, bene, bene.
Oh, now sit here. Sit, sit down, all right.
Oh, adesso sedetevi qui. Sedetevi, sedetevi, bene.
Good, it’s very good. But you have to take out shoes!
Bene, va molto bene. Tu però devi toglierti le scarpe!
See, cannot have shoes here, take out shoes.
Non si possono tenere le scarpe qui, togliti le scarpe.
Take out shoes, everybody’s taken out shoes, take out, take out -
Togliti le scarpe, tutti si sono tolti le scarpe, toglile, toglitele,
take out shoes. Yeah.
togliti le scarpe. Sì.
So come along.
Avanti.
Sit like this, on the sides.
Sedetevi così, ai lati.
[A lato: (Hindi) Shuddhi mein Ganesha Puja?] Pujari (in hindi): Ha, Shri Ganesha Puja.
[A lato: (Hindi) Shuddhi mein Ganesha Puja?] Pujari (in hindi): Ha, Shri Ganesha Puja.
Pujari: To begin with, we will do first the invocation of the puja,
Pujari: Per cominciare reciteremo prima l’invocazione del puja,
then the puja to Lord Ganesha.
poi il puja al Signore Ganesha.
And this would be followed by the puja to the Adi Shakti, Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi.
A questo seguirà il puja all’Adi Shakti, Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi.
In the Devi Bhagavat Purana it is written that the puja to the Adi Shakti
Nel Devi Bhagavat Purana è scritto che il puja all’Adi Shakti
is the greatest puja that can be done by any being.
è il puja più grandioso che possa essere celebrato da qualsiasi essere.
Shri Mataji: That’s why you are privileged.
Shri Mataji: Ecco perché siete privilegiati.
Pujari: Even the Gods don’t do it. Shri Mataji: None of them.
Pujari: Non lo celebrano nemmeno gli dei. Shri Mataji: Nessuno di loro.
They just touch My feet.
Loro toccano soltanto i miei piedi.
None of them did Puja to Me. Believe Me.
Nessuno di loro mi ha fatto un puja. Credetemi.
[Softly, to a little girl - ed] Very good. All right, sit down.
[Parla dolcemente ad una bambina] Benissimo. Va bene, siediti.
Gli yogi: Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Gli yogi: Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
[Most yogis start to repeat the Shri Ganesha mantra
[La maggior parte degli yogi inizia a ripetere il mantra a Shri Ganesha
while a few begin the Mahamantra - ed]
mentre alcuni iniziano con il Mahamantra, ndt]
Shri Mataji: One person should say, then you can repeat, that’s better.
Shri Mataji: Una persona dovrebbe dirlo, dopo voi potete ripeterlo, è meglio.
What about Aradhna, where is she? She has not come? Child: She is upstairs.
E Aradhna, dov’è? Non è venuta? Bambina: È di sopra.
Pujari: We’ll start again. First Lord Ganesha,
Pujari: Ricominciamo. Prima il Signore Ganesha,
then Mahalakshmi, Mahasaraswati, Mahakali.
poi Mahalakshmi, Mahasaraswati, Mahakali.
Then Lord Kalki and then Lord Kalki and Sahastrara Swamini.
Poi il Signore Kalki ed infine il Signore Kalki e Sahastrara Swamini.
Yogi: Three times Shri Ganesha? Pujari: Hm?
Yogi: Tre volte Shri Ganesha? Pujari: Come?
Yogi: How many times the Ganesha mantra? Pujari: Each once, I mean.
Yogi: Quante volte il mantra a Ganesha? Pujari: Intendo ognuno per una volta.
Gli yogi: Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Gli yogi: Om Twameva Sakshat, Shri Ganesha Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi,
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi,
Mahasaraswati, Mahakali Trigunatmika,
Mahasaraswati, Mahakali Trigunatmika,
Kundalini Sakshat, Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Kundalini Sakshat, Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Bhagavati Sakshat, Shri Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Om Twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat,
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji,
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji,
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: Now the names of Lord Vishnu. Om Shri Keshavaya Namah,
Pujari: Ora i nomi del Signore Vishnu. Om Shri Keshavaya Namah,
Om Shri Narayanaya Namah, Om Shri Madhavaya Namah,
Om Shri Narayanaya Namah, Om Shri Madhavaya Namah,
Om Shri Govindaya Namah, Om Shri Vishnuve Namah,
Om Shri Govindaya Namah, Om Shri Vishnuve Namah,
Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah, Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah,
Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah, Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah,
Om Shri Vamanaya Namah, Om Shri Shridharaya Namah,
Om Shri Vamanaya Namah, Om Shri Shridharaya Namah,
Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah, Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah,
Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah, Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah,
Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah, Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah,
Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah, Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah,
Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah, Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah,
Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah, Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah,
Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah, Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah,
Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah, Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah,
Om Shri Achyutaya Namah, Om Shri Janardanaya Namah,
Om Shri Achyutaya Namah, Om Shri Janardanaya Namah,
Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah, Om Shri Damodaraya Namah,
Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah, Om Shri Damodaraya Namah,
Om Shri Upendraya Namah, Om Shri Haraye Namah,
Om Shri Upendraya Namah, Om Shri Haraye Namah,
Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Why these twenty-one names are taken before every puja,
Shri Mataji: Perché questi ventuno nomi sono recitati prima di ogni puja,
even before the today renovation of it?
anche prima del puja così come è stato rinnovato oggi?
First you have to worship Shri Ganesha.
Per prima cosa dovete rendere omaggio a Shri Ganesha.
But even before worshipping why these names are taken,
Ma è importante capire per quale motivo questi nomi siano recitati
is important to understand, everything has a why.
addirittura prima dell’adorazione. Ogni cosa ha un motivo.
Because these are the twenty-one channels within your Sushumna,
Essi rappresentano infatti i ventuno canali all’interno della Sushumna,
twenty-one channels, we should say, in this
anzi, dovremmo dire i ventuno canali compresi
complete Ida, Pingala and Sushumna Nadi.
in tutti e tre i canali principali, cioè Ida, Pingala e Sushumna:
absolutely to give you the ascent, twenty- one channels in Ida, Pingala, Sushumna.
i ventuno canali compresi in tutti e tre i canali, cioè Ida, Pingala e Sushumna.
So one would say seven channels in the Sushumna Nadi.
Si dovrebbe quindi dire che ci sono sette canali nella Sushumna,
But these seven channels are divided multiplied by seven into three.
ma questi sette vanno moltiplicati per tre.
So every channel has got twenty-one (inner? Unclear) channels.
Pertanto, ogni canale consta di ventun canali (interni? Non chiaro).
So Sushumna Nadi has got also twenty-one channels.
Dunque, anche Sushumna nadi ha ventuno canali.
Left-hand side Nadis are as you know that –
Le nadi del lato sinistro sono, come sapete -
perhaps you know, I don’t know if you know the names or not.
forse lo sapete, non so se conosciate i nomi o no.
And the right hand side also, like Gayatri,
Ed anche il lato destro; ad esempio, Gayatri,
Parvati and all these are on the righ hand side.
Parvati e tutti questi nomi sono per il lato destro.
And the left ones are called as Chamundi,
E quelle di lato sinistro sono chiamate Chamundi,
and all these left-sided things, there are seven of them.
e di tutte queste (nadi) del lato sinistro ce ne sono sette.
Now, the central path has got twenty-one channels and has got twenty-one powers.
Ora, il sentiero centrale ha ventuno canali e ventuno poteri.
And their deities are named
E le loro deità hanno nomi
according to the twenty-one aspects of Shri Vishnu.
che si accordano con i ventuno aspetti di Shri Vishnu.
And that’s why these twenty-one aspects are first said,
Ecco perché questi ventuno aspetti sono invocati per primi,
so that within you all these twenty-one channels are awakened.
affinché tutti questi ventuno canali siano risvegliati in voi.
Within you, first of all.
Innanzitutto dentro di voi.
Puja is a double thing, that a cup has to be made
Il puja ha un doppio aspetto: una coppa deve essere creata
and then this source has to be opened out.
e poi deve essere aperta questa sorgente.
So you are the cup. The Sushumna is the channel you have by which you suck in.
Voi siete la coppa, la Sushumna è il canale che avete mediante il quale voi assorbite.
So to open the Sushumna these twenty-one names are said.
Questi ventuno nomi vengono dunque recitati per aprire la Sushumna.
Now, why first Shri Ganesha?
Ora, perché prima Shri Ganesha?
Because Shri Ganesha is the beginning of the desire. And the end of the desire.
Perché Shri Ganesha è l’inizio del desiderio ed è la fine del desiderio.
You start with Ganesha and end up with Ganesha.
Voi iniziate con Ganesha e finite con Ganesha.
And that’s why Shri Ganesha is worshipped.
Ed ecco perché si rende omaggio a Shri Ganesha.
Is the other way round now, the source.
Ora, l’altro aspetto è la sorgente.
When you direct your attention to the source you worship it,
Quando dirigete l’attenzione alla sorgente, la adorate
and when you want to incite or open out your own being, then you chant it.
e, quando volete stimolare o aprire il vostro essere, intonate un mantra.
This is the difference between worship and a mantra.
Questa è la differenza tra l’adorazione e il recitare un mantra.
If you just say mantra, you open yourself up.
Se semplicemente dite un mantra, vi aprite.
But when you worship and chant, then you tap the source.
Ma quando venerate e contemporaneamente intonate un mantra,
I don’t know if I’ve said this before or not.
Non so se l’ho già detto oppure no. Yogi: No, no, no. Shri Mataji: No? Va bene.
That’s how you understand the puja part.
E così che capite la parte relativa al puja.
Now, those who are newcomers, their cup is completely useless.
Ora, la coppa delle persone nuove è del tutto inutile.
And when you excite the deities, they get busy opening their cups,
E quando voi sollecitate le deità, esse si impegnano ad aprire le loro coppe
everybody’s cups also. So it’s a double work.
ed anche le coppe di tutti. È dunque un lavoro doppio.
But if your cup is ready, it’s very easy to fill in.
Ma se la vostra coppa è pronta, è molto facile colmarla.
So now these twenty-one names I think you should take again
Penso dunque che adesso dovreste recitare di nuovo questi ventuno nomi
with the understanding, is better. All right.
con cognizione di causa, è meglio. Bene.
Pujari: Om Shri Keshavaya Namah, Om Shri Narayanaya Namah,
Pujari: Om Shri Keshavaya Namah, Om Shri Narayanaya Namah,
Om Shri Madhavaya Namah, Om Shri Govindaya Namah,
Om Shri Madhavaya Namah, Om Shri Govindaya Namah,
Om Shri Vishnuve Namah, Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah,
Om Shri Vishnuve Namah, Om (Shri) Madhusudanaya Namah,
Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah, Om Shri Vamanaya Namah,
Om Shri Trivikramaya Namah, Om Shri Vamanaya Namah,
Om Shri Shridharaya Namah, Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah,
Om Shri Shridharaya Namah, Om Shri Hrishikeshaya Namah,
Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah, Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah,
Om Shri Sankarshanaya Namah, Om Shri Vasudevaya Namah,
Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah, Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah,
Om Shri Pradyumnaya Namah, Om Shri Aniruddhaya Namah,
Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah, Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah,
Om Shri Purushottamaya Namah, Om Shri Aghokshajaya Namah,
Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah, Om Shri Achyutaya Namah,
Om Shri Narasimhaya Namah, Om Shri Achyutaya Namah,
Om Shri Janardanaya Namah, Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah,
Om Shri Janardanaya Namah, Om Shri Padmanabhaya Namah,
Om Shri Damodaraya Namah, Om Shri Upendraya Namah,
Om Shri Damodaraya Namah, Om Shri Upendraya Namah,
Om Shri Haraye Namah, Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Om Shri Haraye Namah, Om Shri Krishnaye Namah.
Pujari e gli yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Pujari e gli yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Now.
Shri Mataji: Ora.
Pujari: Now we have the mantra for pranayama.
Pujari: Adesso c’è il mantra per Pranayama. Shri Mataji: Questo è il Gayatri,
Pujari: Pranayama. Shri Mataji: Pranayama is the same thing. Is for –
Pujari: Pranayama. Shri Mataji: Pranayama è la stessa cosa. È per…
Prana is right side. It’s physical side. You are opening the right side.
Prana è il lato destro, il lato fisico. Voi state aprendo il lato destro.
You see, this Gayatri mantra you say. Bhur Bhuva Swaha and all these things.
Voi recitate questo mantra Gayatri: Bhur Bhuva Swaha e tutto il resto.
Now, Bhu is Pruthvi, Bhuva is Antariksha,
Ebbene, Bhu è Pruthvi, Bhuva è Antariksha,
you see, like that, it’s all the centers [Pujari: “Swaha”],
sapete, così, rappresenta tutti i centri [Pujari: “Swaha”],
the essence of the centers, you see? Now, Antariksha –
l’essenza dei centri, capite? Ora, Antariksha –
you’ll be surprised that you are the essence of all the Antariksha,
sarete sorpresi di essere l’essenza di tutto l’Antariksha,
your centers are. Yes.
i vostri centri lo sono. Sì.
Pujari [recites Pranayama prayer]: “Pranavasya Parabrahma rishi
Pujari [recita la preghiera a Pranayama]: “Pranavasya Parabrahma rishi
Paramatma Devata, Devi Gayatri chandah. Pranayame viniyogah.”
Paramatma Devata, Devi Gayatri chandah. Pranayame viniyogah.”
Shri Mataji: You do it only with the one nose? Yogi: Both noses. (Not audible)
Shri Mataji: Lo fai solo con una narice? Yogi: Con entrambe le narici. (Non chiaro)
Shri Mataji: Both the noses. Prana: Prana is right side.
Shri Mataji: Entrambe le narici. Prana: prana è il lato destro.
Prana shakti is right side, Mana shakti is left side.
L’energia di prana è il lato destro. L’energia di mana è il lato sinistro.
So Prana shakti you are exciting
In questo modo stimolate l’energia prana
because this prana is the one which spreads in the body,
perché il prana è quello che si diffonde nel corpo,
gives you the balance, which takes in and gives out.
che vi dà equilibrio, che riceve all’interno e che butta fuori.
Pujari: Now we have the Gayatri mantra.
Pujari: Adesso abbiamo il mantra Gayatri.
Aum bhū, Om bhuvah,
Om bhū, Om bhuvah,
Aum swah, Aum mah,
Om swah, Om mah,
Aum janah, Aum tapah, Aum satyam,
Om janah, Om tapah, Om satyam,
Aum tat-Savitru-varenyam, bhargo devasya dhī-mahi
Om tat-Savitru-varenyam, bhargo devasya dhī-mahi
Dhiyo-yo’nah prachodayāt Aum āpo jyotiras’omṛutam
Dhiyo-yo’nah prachodayāt Om āpo jyotiras’omṛutam
Brahma bhūr-bhuvah swar’om
Brahma bhūr-bhuvah swar’om
Pujari e yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Pujari e yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: Om Sriman Maha-Ganadhipataye namah,
Pujari: Om Sriman Maha-Ganadhipataye namah,
Ishta devata-bhyo namah, kula-devata-bhyo namah,
Ishta devata-bhyo namah, kula-devata-bhyo namah,
grama-devata-bhyo namah. Shri Mataji: These are all pertaining to you.
grama-devata-bhyo namah. Shri Mataji: Tutti questi riguardano voi.
Kula Devata is your dynasty, from where you come. There is a god who looks after that.
Kula Devata è la stirpe dalla quale provenite. C’è una deità che la protegge.
Then Grama Devata, of this village. There is a god who looks after this.
Poi Grama Devata, per questo villaggio. C’è una deità che lo protegge.
Is all for you, pertaining to you. Then -
(Questi mantra) sono tutti per voi, riguardano voi. Poi?
Kula Devata? Pujari: Ishta Devata. Shri Mataji: Ishta, the One -
(Dopo) Kula Devata? Pujari: Ishta Devata. Shri Mataji: Ishta, Colui -
your Ishta Devata is Me.
il vostro Ishta Devata sono io.
Ishta means to whom we worship.
Ishta significa l’oggetto della nostra adorazione.
Pujari: Then: Sthana-devata-bhyo namah.
Pujari: Poi: Sthana-devata-bhyo namah.
Shri Mataji: The god, the god that resides in this area.
Shri Mataji: Il dio, il dio che risiede in quest’area.
Means the Divine part that it resides
Indica l’aspetto divino che risiede
Pujari: Vastu-devata-bhyo namah.
Pujari: Vastu-devata-bhyo namah.
Shri Mataji: The one – I don’t know if they do vastu here, but in every house in India
Shri Mataji: Colui - non so se qui facciano vastu ma in ogni casa indiana
they put a kind of a vastu, means they put certain things
mettono una specie di vastu, ossia mettono alcune cose
inside the foundation to protect the house.
dentro le fondamenta per proteggere la casa.
Pujari: Mata pitrubhyam namah.
Pujari: Mata pitrubhyam namah.
Shri Mataji: And your mother and father they are to be worshipped –
Shri Mataji: Inoltre, vostra madre e vostro padre devono essere onorati –
they are to be saluted because you are part of them.
devono essere omaggiati poiché siete parte di loro.
Pujari: Shri Lakshmi-Narayanabhyam namah.
Pujari: Shri Lakshmi-Narayanabhyam namah.
Sarvebhyo devebhyo namoh namah. Sarvebhyo…
Sarvebhyo devebhyo namoh namah. Sarvebhyo…
Shri Mataji: Lakshmi Narayan is, why… again see, Lakshmi Narayan.
Shri Mataji: Lakshmi Narayan perché… guardate, di nuovo Lakshmi Narayan.
More insistence on Lakshmi Narayan, again, because of the Sushumna, again.
Di nuovo si insiste ancora su Lakshmi Narayan, ancora a causa della Sushumna.
The Void. Lakshmi Narayana. Sarva devobhyo Gurubhyo…
Il Void. Lakshmi Narayana. Sarva devobhyo Gurubhyo…
Pujari: Ah. Sarva gurubhyo Namah.
Pujari: Ah. Sarva gurubhyo Namah.
Shri Mataji: All for your ascent, you see?
Shri Mataji: Tutto per la vostra ascesa, vedete?
Pujari: Sarvebhyo-brahmanebhyo namah. Shri Mataji: All those who are
Pujari: Sarvebhyo-brahmanebhyo namah. Shri Mataji: Tutti coloro che sono
realized souls to be really saluted.
anime realizzate devono essere realmente omaggiati.
All has to do with the ascent, see? How clear-cut it is.
È tutto in relazione con l’ascesa, vedete? Com’è chiaro!
Pujari: Now the twelve names of Lord Ganesha.
Pujari: Ora i dodici nomi del Signore Ganesha.
Shri Mataji: Now. The twelve names of Ganesha because Ganesha must be
Shri Mataji: Ora. I dodici nomi di Ganesha in quanto Ganesha deve essere
awakened within you to begin with first, you see,
risvegliato dentro di voi all’inizio, per prima cosa, sapete.
He must be first of all, and then open the source of Ganesha. Let’s have it.
Prima di tutto Lui deve (essere risvegliato) e poi aprite la sorgente di Ganesha.
Kapilo Gajakarnakah, Lambodarascha, Vikato, Vignanasho Ganadhipah
Kapilo Gajakarnakah, Lambodarascha, Vikato, Vignanasho Ganadhipah
Dhumra-ketur-Ganadhyaksho, Bala-chandro Gajananah
Dhumra-ketur-Ganadhyaksho, Bala-chandro Gajananah
Dvadash-aitani Namani, yah patet shrunu-yad-api
Dvadash-aitani Namani, yah patet shrunu-yad-api
vidya-rambhe vivahe-cha, praveshe nirgame tata
vidya-rambhe vivahe-cha, praveshe nirgame tata
sangrame sankate-chaiva, vignas tasya na jayate.
sangrame sankate-chaiva, vignas tasya na jayate.
Then all the mantras of the various Devas and Devis.
Poi tutti i mantra dei vari dei e dee.
Shukl-ambara-dharam devam, shashi-varnam chatur-bhujam
Shukl-ambara-dharam devam, shashi-varnam chatur-bhujam
prasanna-vadanam dhyayet, sarva vignopa-shantaye.
prasanna-vadanam dhyayet, sarva vignopa-shantaye.
Sarva-mangala mangalye, Shive sarva-arta sadhike
Sarva-mangala mangalye, Shive sarva-arta sadhike
sharanye tryambake Gauri, Narayani namostute.
sharanye tryambake Gauri, Narayani namostute.
Sarvada sarva karyeshu, nasti tesham amangalam
Sarvada sarva karyeshu, nasti tesham amangalam
yesham hridisto bhagavan, mangalayatanam harih.
yesham hridisto bhagavan, mangalayatanam harih.
Tadeva lagnam sudinam tadeva, tara-balam chandra-balam tadeva
Tadeva lagnam sudinam tadeva, tara-balam chandra-balam tadeva
vidya balam daiva-balam tadeva, lakshmi-pateh tenghri yugam smarami.
vidya balam daiva-balam tadeva, lakshmi-pateh tenghri yugam smarami.
Labhas-tesham jayastesham kutastesham parajayah… Shri Mataji: Tesham.
Labhas-tesham jayastesham kutastesham parajayah… Shri Mataji: Tesham.
Labhas-tesham, to Them. Labhas-tesham.
Labhas-tesham, a loro. Labhas-tesham.
Pujari: Yesham indivara shyame hridayaste janardanah.
Pujari: Yesham indivara shyame hridayaste janardanah.
Shri Mataji: All - all about Shri Krishna. All about Shri Vishnu.
Shri Mataji: Tutto, tutto ciò che riguarda Shri Krishna.
Pujari: Vinayakam, Gurum bhanum, Brahma-Vishnu-Maheshwaram
Pujari: Vinayakam, Gurum bhanum, Brahma-Vishnu-Maheshwaram
Saraswatim pranamyadau sarva karyarta siddhaye.
Saraswatim pranamyadau sarva karyarta siddhaye.
Abhipa-sitartha siddhyartham pujito yah surah suraih
Abhipa-sitartha siddhyartham pujito yah surah suraih
sarva-vighna haras tasmai Ganadhi pataye namah.
sarva-vighna haras tasmai Ganadhi pataye namah.
Shri Mataji: Oh, Shri Ganesha’s. Pujari: Yes.
Shri Mataji: Oh, quelli di Shri Ganesha. Pujari: Sì.
(More mantras)
(Altri mantra)
Now we say where this puja is being - all, the time and… Shri Mataji: Yes.
Adesso diciamo dove viene (celebrato) il puja: tutto, l’ora e… Shri Mataji: Sì.
Pujari: Srimad bhagavato mahapurushasya vishnurajnaya pravartamanasya,
Pujari: Srimad bhagavato mahapurushasya vishnurajnaya pravartamanasya,
adya brahmano-dvitiya parardhe vishnupade, sri svetavaraha kalpe,
adya brahmano-dvitiya parardhe vishnupade, sri svetavaraha kalpe,
vaivasvata manvantare - Krita Yuge -
vaivasvata manvantare - Krita Yuge -
England varshe - Europe kande - Cheltenham deshe.
England varshe - Europe kande - Cheltenham deshe.
Shri Mataji: Ne - now why was what… Pujari: Why was what - Manvantare, Mother.
Shri Mataji: Perché era quello…? Pujari: Perché era… Manvantare, Madre.
Shri Mataji: Accha (hindi: yes). Pujari: Krita Yuge.
Shri Mataji: Accha (hindi: sì). Pujari: Krita Yuge.
Shri Mataji: Hm, Kruta Yuge… (hindi).
Shri Mataji: Hm, Kruta Yuge… (hindi).
It’s Kruta Yuge, this is time when you have to do something.
È Kruta Yuge, è il momento in cui dovete fare qualcosa,
Something will actualize, something will work out. This is Kruta Yuga.
in cui si realizzerà qualcosa, qualcosa funzionerà. Questo è Kruta Yuga.
Pujari: Thames uttara tire,
Pujari: Thames uttara tire,
varshaa grishme, shraavana mase,
varshaa grishme, shraavana mase,
shukla pakshe, navami thatau…
shukla pakshe, navami thatau…
(Mantras continue)
(I mantra continuano)
[In the meantime Shri Mataji says: “Yes” to a child while
[Shri Mataji dice: “Sì” ad una bambina
teaching her to keep her hands open.]
mentre le insegna a tenere le mani aperte, ndt]
Mataji Nirmala Devi priityartam - Sarva devi deva…
Mataji Nirmala Devi priityartam - Sarva devi deva…
Pujari e gli yogi: … Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Pujari e gli yogi: … Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: (continues with mantras).
(Il pujari continua con i mantra)
Shri Mataji: Shoda Shopachaar. Shoda see, is sixteen.
Shri Mataji: Shoda Shopachaar. Shoda, vedete, significa sedici.
Pujari: Yes. Shoda Shopachaar. Shri Mataji: Hm. Yes. See,
Pujari: Sì. Shoda Shopachaar. Shri Mataji: Hm. Vedete,
whatever I have got, my knowledge, whatever we have got,
qualsiasi cosa io abbia, la mia conoscenza, tutto ciò che abbiamo,
our knowledge, you see, and whatever things we have got,
la nostra conoscenza e qualsiasi cosa abbiamo,
whatever we have got, means whatever we’ve got with us,
tutto ciò che abbiamo, insomma, qualsiasi cosa abbiamo con noi,
we worship You, oh Mother.
noi Ti veneriamo, O Madre.
With our sixteen ways of worship we do to You.
Lo facciamo con i nostri sedici mezzi di adorazione.
[Pujari continues with mantras]
(Il pujari continua con i mantra)
Pujari: Now we start Ganesha Puja.
Pujari: Ora iniziamo il puja a Ganesha.
Shri Mataji: All right. [Hindi].
Shri Mataji: Bene. (Hindi).
[To the children] Please sit down comfortably, all right?
(Ai bambini:) Per favore, sedetevi comodamente, va bene?
All of you should sit nicely.
Dovreste sedervi tutti per bene.
(Hindi)
(Hindi)
All right. Come along, all the children. [Sanskrit mantras]
Bene. Vengano avanti tutti i bambini. (Il pujari continua con i mantra)…
Wakra tunda mahakaya suryakoti sammaprabha
Wakra tunda mahakaya suryakoti sammaprabha
nirvighnam kuru me deva sarva karyeshu sarvada.
nirvighnam kuru me deva sarva karyeshu sarvada.
[More mantras for Ganesha]
(Altri mantra per Ganesha)
Shri Mataji: (Hindi)
Shri Mataji: (Hindi)
Wash My Feet.
Lavate i miei piedi.
Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha
Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha
Shri Mahaganapatayé Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Shri Mahaganapatayé Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah…
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah…
Shri Mataji: …Too much. …You do it later, you and Kalpana - (She corrects Herself)
Shri Mataji: …Troppo. Tu fallo dopo, tu e Kalpana… (si corregge)…
Aradhna, alright? Just wait here. Just wash it, wash it. …
Aradhna, va bene? Aspetta qui. Lavali, lavali…
Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Snanam Samarpayami. [More mantras to Shri Mahaganapati are recited]
Snanam Samarpayami. [Vengono recitati altri mantra a Shri Mahaganapati]
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Yajnopavitam Samarpayami. [More mantras to Mahaganapati]
Yajnopavitam Samarpayami. [Altri mantra per Mahaganapati]
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
[More mantras to Shri Mahaganapati are recited]
[Vengono recitati altri mantra a Shri Mahaganapati]
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swaha Mahaganapatayé Namah
Alankarathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Alankarathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
[Mantras continue]
[I mantra continuano]
Shri Mataji: …Aradhna [hindi]. Now let them do it, come along. Now… [hindi].
Shri Mataji: …Aradhna… (hindi). Adesso fallo fare a loro, avanti. Ora… (hindi).
Pujari: This is Shri Ganesha Atharva Sheersham.
Pujari: Questo è Shri Ganesha Atharva Shirsham.
Shri Mataji: … That’s little [unclear]…
Shri Mataji: …È poco (parlando ad un bambino o bambina – non chiaro)…
Pujari and the yogis: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Il pujari e gli yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Better…(hindi)… she’ll be better.
Shri Mataji: Meglio…(hindi)… starà meglio.
[Pujari aside: “Finished the Ganesha Puja”]
[Il Pujari a lato: “Il Ganesha Puja è finito”]
Shri Mataji: Now, Gavin? Gavin: …finished with the Ganesha Puja.
Shri Mataji: Ora, Gavin? Gavin: …finito il Ganesha Puja.
Shri Mataji: Hm? (Hindi) Pujari: Ganesha Puja… Shri Mataji: Hm?
Shri Mataji: Come? (Hindi) Pujari: Ganesha Puja… Shri Mataji: Come?
Pujari: Finished the Ganesha Puja. Shri Mataji: Kya? (Hindi meaning what?)
Pujari: Ganesha Puja… Shri Mataji: Kya? (Hindi: “Che cosa?”)
Pujari: Ganesha Puja is finished now. Shri Mataji: Finished now.
Pujari: Il puja a Ganesha ora è terminato. Shri Mataji: Adesso è finito.
[Hindi conversation. Pujari: “Take two mantras”…
[conversazione in hindi. Pujari: “Recitare due mantra”…
conversation in Hindi continues].
la conversazione in Hindi continua].
Pujari: Take this water? Shri Mataji: Take it to wipe My feet.
Pujari: Prendiamo quest’acqua? Shri Mataji: Prendi questo per asciugare i miei piedi.
This water can be – [Pujari resumes mantras in Sanskrit]
Quest’acqua può essere… [Il pujari riprende la recitazione dei mantra in sanscrito]
better to put it on the Sahastrara of everyone. Specially the children.
è meglio metterla sul Sahastrara di tutti. Specialmente dei bambini (hindi).
Shri Mataji: Now let them do it. Aradhna? …
Shri Mataji: Adesso fallo fare a loro. Aradhna? …
[Pujari speaks probably in Hindi or Sanskrit.
(Il pujari parla probabilmente in hindi o sanscrito
Shri Mataji replies and then in English: … or puja we will do.
Shri Mataji risponde e poi dice in inglese:) … oppure passeremo al puja.
There’s nothing beyond, eh?
Non c’è niente oltre questo, vero?
Pujari: It is the worship of the picture as a representation of the universe,
Pujari: È la venerazione dell’immagine, come rappresentazione dell’Universo,
which is present in front in the form of Shri Mataji.
ed è presente di fronte (a noi) nella forma di Shri Mataji.
[Then mantras in Sanskrit follow]
(seguono dei mantra in sanscrito).
Now the mantra of the earth, to stabilize our puja.
Ora il mantra della terra per stabilizzare il nostro puja
[long mantra to Pruthvi]
(lungo mantra a Pruthvi, il principio della terra).
Now we are asking all the horrible things to go away, the bhuts and …
Ora chiediamo che tutte le cose orribili se ne vadano, i bhut e…
[Mantras in Sanskrit follow].
(Mantra in sanscrito)
Now we perform six things to purify our body,
Adesso eseguiamo sei cose per purificare il nostro corpo,
we touch six parts of our body.
tocchiamo sei parti del nostro corpo.
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Hridayaya Namah.
Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Hridayaya Namah.
Shri Mataji: First is heart, is important.
Shri Mataji: La prima è il cuore, è importante.
Pujari: Next, the head. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shirsay Swaha.
Pujari: Poi la testa. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shirsay Swaha.
Next the back of your head, yes. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Poi la parte posteriore della testa, sì. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Om – next to form a protection around us.
Om – la prossima per dare una protezione intorno a noi.
Shri Mataji: Vashak is like this, you see: Va Shak. Is a bandhan.
Shri Mataji: Vashak è così, guardate: “Va”, “Shak”. È un bandhan.
Pujari: So, Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Pujari: Dunque, Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Shikayay Vashak.
Then kavacha, Mataji… Shri Mataji: Kavach. Is a bandhan, yes.
Poi il Kavacha, Mataji. Shri Mataji: Kavach. È un bandhan, sì.
Like this you can do it. Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Kavachaya Swah.
Potete farlo in questo modo. Pujari: Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Kavachaya Swah.
Pujari: Next the eyes, and the Agnya chakra. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Nitrayaya Vashak.
Pujari: Poi gli occhi e l’Agnya chakra. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Nitrayaya Vashak.
Pujari: Next we put a bandhan. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Astraya Phat.
Pujari: Poi diamo un bandhan. Om Bhur Bhuva Swaha Astraya Phat.
(Pujari aside: “…bandhan”) Shri Mataji: Do like this.
(Pujari a lato: “…bandhan”) Shri Mataji: Fate così.
Astra. Astra means the weapon.
Astra. Astra significa arma.
[Pujari recites more Sanskrit mantras]
(Il pujari recita altri mantra in sanscrito)
Pujari: Now we invoke all the rivers. Gange cha yamune chaiva godavari
Pujari: Adesso invochiamo tutti i fiumi. Gange cha yamune chaiva godavari
sarasvati narmade sindhu kaveri jale'smin sannidhim kuru.
sarasvati narmade sindhu kaveri jale'smin sannidhim kuru.
Now we salute the pitcher: kalashaya namah
Adesso rendiamo omaggio alla brocca: kalashaya namah
[Sanskrit invocation follows].
(segue invocazione in sanscrito).
Now we worship the conch.
Ora rendiamo omaggio alla conchiglia
Next the bell.
Poi la campana.
Shri Mataji: What is it? Pujari: Gantha.
Shri Mataji: Che cos’è? Pujari: Gantha.
This signifies the arrival of all the Devas and the departure of all the rakshasas.
Annuncia l’arrivo di tutti gli dei e l’allontanamento di tutti i rakshasa.
Next prayer to the lamp. [Mantras are recited]
Segue la preghiera alla lampada. (Recitazione di mantra)
Now the main puja, puja begins.
Ora il puja principale, il puja comincia.
[Sanskrit mantras – then prayer to Vishnu:]
mantra in sanscrito – poi preghiera a Vishnu:]
Pujari: Now the mantras of the Goddess.
Pujari: Adesso i mantra della Dea.
Namo Devyai Mahaa-Devyai Shivaayai Satatam Namah
Namo Devyai Mahaa-Devyai Shivaayai Satatam Namah
Namah Prakrtyai Bhadraayai Niyataah Prannataah Sma Taam.
Namah Prakrtyai Bhadraayai Niyataah Prannataah Sma Taam.
(mantra continues).
(la recitazione dei mantra continua)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Avahanam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Avahanam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now the Avahana.
Shri Mataji: Adesso l’Avahana.
After awakening yourself, awakening all your channels,
Dopo aver risvegliato voi stessi, dopo aver risvegliato tutti i vostri canali,
now the Avahana is the calling, now you are inviting your Mother.
ora l’Avahana è l’invocazione, adesso state invitando vostra Madre.
This is the nimantranam, this is the way you are inviting.
Questo è il nimantranam, è il modo in cui la invitate.
[Shri Mataji calls one child to wash Her Feet] [Hindi].
[Shri Mataji chiama una bambina a lavare i piedi] [Hindi].
Pujari: (continues with mantras)
Pujari: (continua con dei mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Asanathe Akshatam Samarpayami.
(Continues with mantras)
(La recitazione dei mantra continua).
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Padyam Samarpayami.
Padyam is the washing of the Feet of the Divine Mother.
Padyam è il lavaggio dei piedi della Madre Divina.
(Continues with mantras)
(Continua con altri mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Arghyam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now it is very interesting, in Sanskrit language,
Shri Mataji: Ora, è molto interessante. In sanscrito,
when you are using the water
quando si usa l’acqua per lavare i piedi della Dea, è detta Padyam.
When you are giving water for Mother to drink, it’s Arghyam.
Quando si offre acqua da bere alla Madre, è Arghyam - la parola cambia, sapete.
Once it is for the Goddess, or for Gods, then the word is different.
Quando si riferisce alla Dea, o alle deità, il termine cambia.
For other people it is just water – they call it nira, jalam, anything.
Per tutti gli altri è semplicemente acqua, la chiamano nira, jalam, in qualsiasi modo.
But for the Goddess it is padyam. Arghyam. Asanam. Pujari: Udaka also.
Ma per la Dea è padyam, arghyam, asanam. Pujari: Anche Udaka.
Shri Mataji: Eh? Pujari: Udaka. Shri Mataji: Udaka, Udaka also.
Shri Mataji: Eh? Pujari: Udaka. Shri Mataji: Udaka, anche Udaka.
Pouring the water – the water that is poured is called as Udak.
Versare l’acqua… l’acqua che si versa è chiamata Udak.
No other language has this. Pujari: Yes. Shri Mataji: No language –
Questo non esiste in nessun’altra lingua. Pujari: Sì. Shri Mataji: In nessuna lingua.
only except in English I think they call God “Thou”,
Ad eccezione solo dell’inglese, dove penso si rivolgano a Dio con “Thou”;
perhaps, maybe. Pujari: That is the limit. Shri Mataji: Eh?
forse, magari. Pujari: Quello è il massimo. Shri Mataji: Come?
Pujari: That is the limit. Shri Mataji: That’s the limit. No more!
Pujari: Quello è il massimo. Shri Mataji: Quello è il massimo. Niente di più.
For God if we call Thou You should be satisfied!
Se ci rivolgiamo a Dio dandogli del Tu dovrebbe essere soddisfatto!.
Yes, good. [Pujari continues with mantras.
Sì, bene. (Il pujari continua con i mantra)
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Acchamanayam Samarpayami.
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Acchamanayam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Acchamanayam: whatever used, for… Pujari: Sipping.
Shri Mataji: Acchamanayam: tutto ciò che è usato per … Pujari: Sorseggiare.
Shri Mataji: Sipping, you see. Acchaman is sipping.
Shri Mataji: Sorseggiare, sapete. Acchaman è sorseggiare.
Of the Mother, is called as Acchamani.
Quando riguarda la Madre si dice Acchamani.
[Pujari recites names of Indian rivers in Sanskrit]
[Il pujari recita in sanscrito i nomi dei fiumi indiani]
Shri Mataji: All these rivers I bring to Your Feet to give You bath.
Shri Mataji: Conduco ai Tuoi piedi tutti questi fiumi per farTi il bagno.
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Snamayam Samarpayami.
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Snamayam Samarpayami.
Gavin: See, we are near the sources of two great rivers of this country here.
Gavin: Vede, qui siamo vicini alla sorgente di due importanti fiumi di questo paese.
Shri Mataji: What is that? Gavin: The Thames and Severn both start very close to here.
Shri Mataji: Quali? Gavin: Il Tamigi ed il Severn nascono entrambi molto vicino a qui.
Shri Mataji: Here? It’s Thames and…? Gavin: Severn. Yogi: Severn doesn’t start here.
Shri Mataji: Qui? Il Tamigi ed il…? Gavin: Severn. Yogi: Il Severn non nasce qui.
Gavin, No, but there’s a tributary for it just… Yes.
Gavin: No, ma c’è un suo affluente proprio… Sì.
Shri Mataji: Is it? Thames starts from here? Yogi: But the most (?)
Shri Mataji: Davvero? Il Tamigi nasce da qui? Yogi: La più famosa
famous of all the springs that come out of the earth is Cheltenham, Mother.
di tutte le sorgenti che scaturiscono dalla terra è Cheltenham, Madre.
Yogis: Spa. Shri Mataji: Spa: ah!
Gli yogi: Una Spa. Shri Mataji: Una Spa, ah!
Pujari: Now we offer ghee to Shri Mataji.
Pujari: Adesso offriamo il ghee a Shri Mataji.
Should we take another for You?
Dovremmo prenderne un altro per Lei?
Shri Mataji: Ghee is to be offered.
Shri Mataji: Il ghee deve essere offerto.
You see, if you want to use the Feet water this time then do it,
Sapete, se questa volta volete usare l’acqua dei piedi, fatelo,
it’s good, all right, start. Better do it, it’s good.
bene, va bene, cominciate. Meglio farlo, va bene.
Pujari: (recites Sanskrit mantras)
Pujari: (recita mantra in sanscrito)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Ghruta snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Ghruta snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Nextly come milk.
Poi viene il latte.
Shri Mataji: Shuddhodaka, now water has to be poured out.
Shri Mataji: Shuddhodaka, adesso deve essere versata l’acqua.
Pujari: Pure – not just – pure water.
Pujari: Pura – non solo… acqua pura.
Shri Mataji: But Shuddhodaka - is all right, pure water.
Shri Mataji: Ma Shuddhodaka – è giusto, acqua pura.
Shuddhodaka - not even water it is, it is the water that is to be pured - poured,
Shuddhodaka – non è nemmeno acqua, è l’acqua che deve essere versata,
is Shuddhodaka; and Shuddha is the pure.
è Shuddhodaka; e Shuddha significa pura.
Pujari: (Mantras)
Pujari: (Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Paya snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Paya snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Next we offer curd to Shri Mataji. Shri Mataji: Little hot – more hot water.
Poi offriamo yogurt a Shri Mataji. Shri Mataji: Un po’ calda, ancora acqua calda.
Pujari: (Mantras)
Pujari: (Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah dadhi snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah dadhi snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Next, honey. Now we offer honey to Shri Mataji.
Poi il miele. Adesso offriamo miele a Shri Mataji.
(Mantras)
(Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah madhu snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah madhu snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Milk has to be more. More milk.
Shri Mataji: Il latte deve essere di più. Altro latte.
It’s all right, you can pour more milk now. In out of proportion it is.
Va bene, adesso puoi versare altro latte. È sproporzionato.
Let’s keep heated milk, it is better, it doesn’t matter.
Manteniamo il latte caldo, è meglio, non importa.
It should all go away when you put the sugar.
Dovrebbe andare via tutto quando mettete lo zucchero.
Pujari: Next we offer sugar to Shri Mataji.
Pujari: Poi offriamo lo zucchero a Shri Mataji.
Has been pured from the sugarcane.
È stato purificato dalla canna da zucchero.
(Sanskrit mantras)
(Mantra in sanscrito)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah sharkara snanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah sharkara snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shuddhodaka snanam samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now rub it on My Feet (the sugar – ed.). Would be better.
Shri Mataji: Adesso strofinalo sui miei piedi (lo zucchero, ndt). Sarebbe meglio.
Then the fingers you see, just - it’s still there, quite a lot.
Poi le dita… ce n’è ancora molto.
The chakras are. (Somebody aside: “Shiny!”)
Sono i chakra. (Qualcuno a lato: “Splendenti!”)
Pujari: Next we offer to Shri Mataji three auspicious things
Pujari: Poi offriamo a Shri Mataji tre elementi di buon auspicio
mixed in water: camphor, sandalwood paste and perfume.
mescolati con acqua: canfora, pasta di sandalo e profumo.
(Sanskrit mantras follow)
(Seguono mantra in sanscrito).
Shri Mataji: Now on the Feet. Just pour it.
Shri Mataji: Adesso sui piedi. Versalo.
Now pour the water.
Adesso versa l’acqua.
Too much. Yes, there. (Indistinct).
Troppa. Sì, lì. (Non udibile).
Pujari: Now we are supposed to offer Shri Mataji sindhur,
Pujari: Adesso dovremmo offrire a Shri Mataji sindhur,
tulasi leaves and turmeric powder.
foglie di tulsi e polvere di curcuma.
Shri Mataji: Tulsi, tulsi leaves, first. That’s all, then I’ll remove My Feet.
Shri Mataji: Tulsi, per prima cosa le foglie di tulsi. È tutto, poi sposterò i piedi.
Offer tulsi leaves. Have you got tulasi here?
Offri le foglie di tulsi. Avete qui il tulsi?
Basil. You’ll get it later. All right? Good.
Il basilico? Lo prenderete dopo. Va bene? Bene.
(Sanskrit mantras for offering of tulsi)
(Recitazione di mantra in sanscrito per l’offerta di tulsi)
Now just wipe My Feet, take this out and I’ll put them on the ground,
Adesso asciuga i miei piedi. Togli questo e li appoggerò a terra.
now you can put…
Adesso puoi mettere…
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah bhupam samarpayami.
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah bhupam samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: Now spread something here down below,
Shri Mataji: Adesso stendi qualcosa qui sotto,
put here something else, dry this.
metti qui qualcos’altro, asciuga questo.
Yes. Just the sindhur and this thing, these things you put on My Feet.
Sì. Metti il sindhur e questo, queste cose sui miei piedi.
And must – you must put keshar, keshar you haven’t got.
E devi mettere il keshar, non avete il keshar.
I should have brought keshar.
Avrei dovuto portare il keshar,
lLet’s try, saffron. Pujari: Because here in this country we can get it.
lo zafferano, proviamo. Pujari: Infatti qui, in questo paese, possiamo trovarlo.
Shri Mataji: Saffron you get quite a lot. Pujari: It’s quite easy.
Shri Mataji: Si trova moltissimo zafferano. Pujari: È abbastanza facile.
Shri Mataji: Very easy. Saffron is very good. Now.
Shri Mataji: È molto facile. Lo zafferano è ottimo. Ora.
Pujari: We should take some photographs. Shri Mataji: Hm?
Pujari: Dovremmo scattare qualche fotografia. Shri Mataji: Come?
Shri Mataji: Yes.
fotografia. Shri Mataji: Sì.
Before… even Sahaja yogis…
Prima che anche i sahaja yogi…
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala…
Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala…
Shri Mataji: First put the dried one, have you got the dried?
Shri Mataji: Prima metti quello asciutto, hai quello asciutto?
Just akshata, mix it up in that, it’s all right.
Un po’ di akshata, mescolalo lì dentro, bene.
Just this, you see.
Solo questo, vedi.
Little bit, yes. That’s all.
Un po’, sì. Basta.
Now what else? Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
Adesso cos’altro? Pujari: Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
Bhupam Samarpayami Deepam darshayami.
Bhupam Samarpayami Deepam darshayami.
(Mantras continue)
(I mantra continuano)
Shri Mataji: Now just put that one, yes. Do like this, Gavin.
Shri Mataji: Adesso metti quello, sì. Fai così, Gavin.
Yes. All right.
Sì. Bene.
Pujari: Now to the five forms of Pranayami.
Pujari: Adesso alle cinque forme di Pranayami.
Shri Mataji (to Gavin): Now the karpura (camphor) little bit.
Shri Mataji (a Gavin): Adesso un po’ di karpura (canfora, ndt).
Rub it up.
Strofinala.
Now the offering whatever I have to eat –
Adesso l’offerta di tutto ciò che devo mangiare,
something you have…(indistinct words) sweet or chana will do.
qualcosa che avete… (parole indistinte), dolci o chana (ceci) andranno bene.
Chana, chana is absolutely best, I love chana.
I chana, i chana sono la cosa migliore in assoluto, io adoro i chana.
This is Naivedhyam, you see, just (indistinct).
Questo è Naivedhyam, sapete, proprio… (parole indistinte).
Only the Brahmins eat everything, the Gods don’t eat anything.
Soltanto i bramini mangiano tutto; gli Dei non mangiano nulla.
That’s all right.
Va bene così.
Pujari: Om Shri Pranaya swaha. Shri Mataji: Chana.
Pujari: Om Shri Pranaya swaha. Shri Mataji: Chana.
Pujari: Om Shri Apanaya Swaha. Om Shri Bhyanaya Swaha.
Pujari: Om Shri Apanaya Swaha. Om Shri Bhyanaya Swaha.
Om Shri Uddhanaya swaha. Om Shri Samanaya swaha.
Om Shri Uddhanaya swaha. Om Shri Samanaya swaha.
Om Shri Brahmané swaha. Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Om Shri Brahmané swaha. Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Mataji: Use this thing. Just use this. This one. Warren: Should use this.
Shri Mataji: Usa questo oggetto. Usa questo, questo. Warren: Si dovrebbe usare questo.
Pujari: (Mantras)
Pujari: (Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Mantra Pushpam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Mantra Pushpam Samarpayami.
Namaskaranami
Namaskaranami
(mantras follow).
(seguono mantra).
Now we come to the main puja.
Adesso si passa al puja principale.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Abhisheka Snanam Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Abhisheka Snanam Samarpayami.
Shri Mataji: I know.
Shri Mataji: Lo so.
(Pujari starts recitation of mantras)
(Il pujari inizia la recitazione dei mantra)
This is actually when You are in a statue.
Shri Mataji: Questo in realtà si fa quando si è presenti sotto forma di statua.
SYou can only do all this when You are in a statue.
Si può fare tutto questo solo quando si è in una statua.
Pujari: (Mantras)
Pujari: (Mantra)
Pujari: Now we can - sari, Mataji, vastraya.
Pujari: Adesso possiamo - il sari, Mataji, vastraya (stoffa).
Shri Mataji: Vastra. [Pujari aside: “You got some sari?”] Sari…(hindi).
Shri Mataji: Vastra. [Il pujari a lato a qualcuno: “Avete un sari?”] Sari…(hindi).
What sari? What’s that?
Quale sari? Che cos’è?
No, no, no. Sari’s out of question.
No, no, no. Il sari è fuori questione.
Pujari: Which vastran, then?
Pujari: Quale vastran, allora?
Shri Mataji: Which one they opened within now - anything.
Shri Mataji: Qualunque abbiano aperto ora dentro - qualsiasi.
No, now - any vastran you can use that – do... [Yogi softly: “We could try”]
No, ora – potete usare qualsiasi vastran – fate…
Olympia…
Olympia…
Good.
Brava.
Pujari: (Recitation of mantras)
Pujari: (Recitazione di mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Vastran Samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Vastran Samarpayami.
Aum - Sandal.
Om - Sandalo.
(Mantras for offering of sandal)
(Mantra per l’offerta del sandalo)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah chandanam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah chandanam samarpayami.
Then some more akshata, Mataji. (Mantras)
Poi ancora un po’ di akshata, Mataji. (Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Akshatam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah Akshatam samarpayami.
Now. (More mantras)
Ora. (Altri mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah haridram samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah haridram samarpayami.
Make sindhur offers (kumkum).
Facciamo offerte di sindhur (kumkum).
(Mantras)
(Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kumkumam samarpayami.
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kumkumam samarpayami.
Pujari: (Mantra)
Pujari: (Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kajalam samarpayami. (Offer of kajal)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah kajalam samarpayami. (Offerta di kajal)
(Mantra)
(Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
kantha sutram samarpayami. (Offer of sutra for the neck)
kantha sutram samarpayami. (Offerta del sutra per il collo)
[Shri Mataji speaks in Hindi]
[Shri Mataji parla in hindi]
(Mantra)
(Mantra)
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah
kankanam samarpayami. (Offer of bangles)
kankanam samarpayami. (Offerta dei bracciali)
(More mantras follow)
(Seguono altri mantra)
[Shri Mataji speaks in Hindi]
(Shri Mataji parla in hindi)
Pujari: Shall we do the Sahastranama (…) - Lalita Sahastranama?
Pujari: Leggiamo il Sahastranama (…) - Lalita Sahastranama?
Shri Mataji: [Hindi conversation with pujari.
Shri Mataji: [Conversazione in hindi con il pujari.
“Puja… Havan… Havana…
“Puja… Havan… Havana…
Devi Mahatmya…”. Pujari: “Devi Mahatmyam”]
Devi Mahatmya…”. Pujari: “Devi Mahatmyam”]
No, the - when Mahishasura was killed, you see, this one was read.
No, quando Mahishasura fu ucciso, vedi, è stato letto questo.
So the beginning of it - and then say it, read it in English, would be better.
Quindi inizia, inoltre leggilo in inglese, sarebbe meglio.
[Pujari starts reading in Sanskrit]
[Il pujari inizia a leggere in sanscrito]
If you read it in English would be better. Pujari: Read it in English.
Se tu lo leggessi in inglese sarebbe meglio. Pujari: Leggerlo in inglese.
Shri Mataji: Hm, then whatever is in English is the story.
Shri Mataji: Hm, poi tutta la storia è in inglese. È meglio se capiscono.
(Hindi) All right, stand up and read it.
(Hindi) Va bene, alzati e leggilo.
Pujari: This is the great hymn to the Goddess when She had killed Mahishasura,
Pujari: Questo è il grande inno alla Dea quando ebbe ucciso Mahishasura
whom as we all know is back again in Bangalore.
il quale, come sappiamo tutti, è tornato a Bangalore.
“To that Ambika who is worthy of worship by all the devas and sages,
“A quella Ambika che è degna di adorazione da parte di tutti i Deva e tutti i saggi,
and who pervades this world by Her power,
che pervade il mondo con il Suo potere e che è l’incarnazione dell’intero potere
of all the hosts of Devas, we bow in devotion.
di tutte le schiere dei Deva, noi ci inchiniamo con devozione.
May She grant us auspicious things.
Possa Lei concederci ciò che è di buon auspicio.
May Chandika whose incomparable greatness and power,
Possa Chandika, la cui grandezza e potere incomparabili
Bhagavan Vishnu, Brahma and Hara are unable to describe,
Bhagavan Vishnu, Brahma ed Hara sono incapaci di descrivere,
bestow Her mind on protecting the entire world,
rivolgere la Sua mente alla protezione del mondo intero
and on destroying the fear of evil.
e alla distruzione della paura del male.
Oh Devi, we bow before You. Who are Yourself good fortune
Oh Devi, noi ci inchiniamo a Te che sei la buona fortuna
in the dwellings of the virtuous, and ill-fortune in those of the vicious,
nella casa del virtuoso e la sfortuna in quella del vizioso;
intelligence in the hearts of the learned, faith in the hearts of the good,
intelligenza nei cuori dei sapienti, fede nei cuori dei buoni
and modesty in the hearts of the high-born.
e modestia nel cuore dei nobili di nascita.
May You protect the Universe!
Possa Tu proteggere l’Universo!
Oh Devi, how can we describe Your inconceivable form,
Oh Devi, come possiamo noi descrivere la Tua forma inconcepibile
or Your abundant, surpassing valour that destroys the asuras,
o il Tuo immenso e incomparabile valore che stermina gli asura,
or Your wonderful feats displayed in battles
o le Tue mirabili prodezze mostrate in battaglia
amongst all the hosts of Gods, asuras and others?
in mezzo a tutte le schiere di Dei, asura ed altri?
You are the origin of all the three worlds, though You are possessed of the three gunas,
Tu sei l’origine di tutti i tre mondi; sebbene Tu possieda le tre guna
You are not known to have any of their attendant qualities.
non Ti si conosce nessuna delle qualità che le caratterizzano.
You are incomprehensible even to Vishnu, Shiva and others.
Tu sei incomprensibile persino a Vishnu, Shiva e agli altri.
You are the resort of all. The entire world is composed
Tu sei la dimora di tutto. Il mondo intero è composto
of an infinitesimal portion of Yourself.
di una Tua porzione infinitesimale.
You are verily the Supreme Primordial Prakruti. Untransformed.
Tu sei in verità la suprema Prakruti primordiale. Immutata.
Oh Devi, You are swaha, at whose utterance
O Devi, Tu sei swaha, la cui pronuncia
the whole assemblage of Gods obtain satisfaction in all the sacrifices.
dona soddisfazione all’intera assemblea degli Dei in tutti i sacrifici.
You are the swadha…” Shri Mataji: Same.
Tu sei swadha…” Shri Mataji: La stessa cosa.
Now, these are the mantras of the swaha: Bhuh is pruthvi, is Ganesha Tattwa.
Questi sono dunque i mantra di swaha: Bhuh è pruthvi, il principio di Ganesha.
Then you said swah. Pujari: Yes. Om Bhuh Bhuvah Swah.
Dopo hai detto swah. Pujari: Sì. Om Bhur Bhuvah Swah.
Shri Mataji: Swah is the satisfaction.
Shri Mataji: Swah è la soddisfazione.
Bhuvah is the Antariksha, the whole universe.
Bhuvah è Antariksha, l’intero universo.
Pujari: You are the swadha which gives satisfaction to the manes…
Pujari: Tu sei la swadha che dona soddisfazione ai mani…
Shri Mataji: Swa-dha: swa is your self,
Shri Mataji: Swa-dha: swa è il vostro Sé,
dha means you have sustained yourself with your Self.
dha significa che avete sostenuto voi stessi con il vostro Sé.
Swadha is the quality of the Nabhi chakra.
Swadha è la qualità del Nabhi chakra.
Pujari: “Therefore you are chanted by people.
Pujari: “Per questo sei celebrata dalla gente.
Oh Devi, You are Bhagavati, the Supreme Vidya,
O Devi, Tu sei Bhagavati, la Vidya suprema
which is the cause of liberation and great inconceivable penances.
che è la causa della liberazione e di grandi, inenarrabili penitenze.
You are the Supreme Knowledge, are cultivated by sages who desire liberation,
Tu sei la Suprema Conoscenza coltivata dai saggi che desiderano la liberazione,
whose senses are well restrained and who are devoted to reality
i cui sensi sono ben controllati e che sono devoti alla realtà
and have shed all the blemishes.
e si sono liberati di tutte le imperfezioni.
You are the soul of Shabda-Brahma, You are the repository of the very pure…”
Tu sei l’anima di Shabda-Brahma, Tu sei la depositaria del purissimo…”.
Shri Mataji: Logos, logos you call? - Shabda-Brahma. OM.
Shri Mataji: Il logos, logos lo chiamate? Shabda-Brahma. OM.
“You are the Soul of that”. Pujari: OM. All the Vedas come out of it (unclear).
“Tu ne sei l’anima”. Pujari: OM. Tutti i Veda ne derivano (non chiaro, ndt).
Shri Mataji: Everything is created out of that OM. Shabda-Brahma is OM,
Shri Mataji: Tutto è creato da questo OM. Shabda-Brahma è OM,
and out of that all this Brahma – means Brahmanda - is created, out of OM.
e da questo, da OM è creato tutto questo Brahma, ossia Brahmanda.
Pujari: Shabda-Brahma. Shri Mataji: All the scriptures.
Pujari: Shabda-Brahma. Shri Mataji: Tutte le scritture.
Pujari: “You are the repository of the very pure Rik and Yajus hymns
Pujari: “Tu sei la depositaria dei purissimi inni Rik, Yajus e Sama.
You are Bhagavati, embodying the three Vedas.
Tu sei Bhagavati, incarnazione dei tre Veda.
And You are the sustenance whereby life is maintained.
E Tu sei il sostegno grazie al quale la vita viene preservata.
You are the Supreme Destroyer of the pain of all the worlds.
Tu sei la Suprema Distruttrice del dolore di tutti i mondi.
Oh Devi, You are the intellect, by which
O Devi, Tu sei l’intelletto mediante il quale
the essence of all scriptures is comprehended. You are Durga,
si comprende l’essenza di tutte le scritture. Tu sei Durga,
the boat that takes men across the difficult ocean of worldly existence
l’imbarcazione che trasporta gli uomini attraverso l’oceano dell’esistenza terrena,
devoid of attachments. You are Shri
privi di attaccamenti. Tu sei Shri
who has invariably taken Her abode in the heart of Vishnu.
che ha invariabilmente preso dimora nel cuore di Vishnu.
You are indeed Gauri who has established Herself with Shiva.
In verità Tu sei Gauri che si è unita a Shiva.
Gently smiling, pure, resembling the full moon’s orb,
Dal sorriso gentile, puro, simile al globo della luna piena;
beautiful like the splendor of excellent gold was Your face.
meraviglioso come lo splendore dell’oro purissimo era il Tuo volto.
Yet it was very strange that, being swayed by anger, Mahishasura could not bear it.
Eppure, molto stranamente, Mahishasura, travolto dalla collera,
Far strange it is that after seeing Your wrathful face, O Devi,
Assai strano è, o Devi, che dopo aver visto il Tuo volto adirato,
terrible with its frowns and red in hue like the rising moon,
terribile con la sua espressione aggrottata e rosso come la luna nascente,
that Mahishasura did not immediately give up his life!
Mahishasura non abbia rinunciato all’istante alla sua vita!
For, who can live after beholding the enraged Destroyer?
Chi può vivere, infatti, dopo aver visto la Distruttrice furente?
O Devi, be propitious. You are Supreme.
O Devi, sii propizia. Tu sei la Suprema.
If enraged, you forthwith destroy the (asura) families
Se adirata Tu distruggi all’istante le stirpi degli asura
for the welfare of the world. This was known
per il benessere del mondo. Questo fu noto
the very moment the extensive forces of Mahishasura were brought to their end.
allorché le possenti forze di Mahishasura furono distrutte.
You are always bounteous, to those fortunate ones with whom You are well pleased,
Tu sei sempre generosa con quei fortunati dei quali sei compiaciuta
are indeed the object of esteem in the country,
e, in verità, essi sono oggetto di rispetto nel Paese,
theirs are riches, theirs are glories, and their acts of righteousness perish not;
possiedono ricchezze, gloria e le loro azioni virtuose non periscono.
they are indeed blessed and possessed of devoted children, servants and wives.
Essi sono davvero benedetti e possiedono figli e servitori devoti e mogli devote.
By Your Grace, O Devi, the blessed individual does daily
Per Tua grazia, o Devi, la persona benedetta compie ogni giorno
all righteous deeds with utmost care and thereby attains to heaven.
tutte azioni virtuose con estrema cura e così raggiunge il Cielo.
Are You not, therefore, O Devi, the bestower of reward in all the three worlds?
Non sei dunque Tu, o Devi, Colei che concede ricompense in tutti i tre mondi?
When called to mind in a difficult position, You remove fear from every person.
Se ricordata in una situazione difficile, Tu rimuovi la paura da ogni persona.
When called to mind by those in happiness, You bestow a mind still more pious.
Se ricordata da coloro che sono in gioia, tu concedi una mente ancora più pia.
Which Goddess but You, O Dispeller of poverty, pain and fear,
Quale Dea, se non Tu, che dissipi povertà, dolore e paura,
has an ever sympathetic heart for helping everybody?
ha un cuore sempre partecipe e disposto ad aiutare chiunque?
The world attains happiness by the killing of these foes;
Il mondo raggiunge felicità con la distruzione di questi nemici.
and though these asuras have committed sins enough
E, sebbene questi asura abbiano commesso peccati sufficienti
to keep them long in hell,
a tenerli lungamente all’inferno,
let them reach heaven by meeting death eventually at battle with You.
fa’ che raggiungano il Cielo trovando la morte per mano Tua.
Thinking thus, it is that You, O Devi, certainly destroy our enemies.
È certamente in considerazione di questo, o Devi,
Don’t You reduce to ashes all asuras by mere sight?
Non riduci forse in cenere tutti gli asura con una mera occhiata?
But You direct Your weapons against them so that even the wicked ones,
Ma Tu dirigi le Tue armi contro di loro così che persino i malvagi,
purified by the missiles, may attain higher worlds." Shri Mataji: Yes.
purificati dai proiettili, potrebbero raggiungere i mondi superiori.
Pujari: “Such is Your most kindly intention towards them”.
Tale è la Tua intenzione sommamente benevola nei loro confronti".
Shri Mataji: This one you read again.
Shri Mataji: Questo rileggilo.
Pujari: “Don’t You reduce to ashes all asuras by mere sight?
Pujari: "Non riduci forse in cenere gli asura con una mera occhiata?
But You direct Your weapons against them so that even the wicked ones,
Ma Tu dirigi le Tue armi contro di loro in modo che persino i malvagi,
purified by the missiles, may attain the higher worlds”.
purificati dai proiettili, potrebbero raggiungere i mondi superiori”.
Shri Mataji: May attain. May. Pujari: May.
Shri Mataji: Potrebbero raggiungere. Potrebbero. Pujari: Potrebbero.
“That is Your most kindly intention towards them.”
“Tale è la Tua intenzione sommamente benevola nei loro confronti”.
Shri Mataji: Not promised.
Shri Mataji: Non è una promessa.
Pujari: “If the eyes of the asuras had not been blinded by the terrible flashes
Pujari: “Se gli occhi degli asura non sono stati resi ciechi dai terribili lampi
of the mass of light issuing from Your sword
della massa di luce emessa dalla Tua spada,
or by the copious luster of Your spear point,
o dal copioso splendore della punta della Tua lancia,
it is because they saw also Your face resembling the moon,
è perché hanno visto anche il Tuo volto, simile alla luna,
giving out cool rays.
emettere raggi rinfrescanti.
O Devi, Your nature is to subdue the conduct of the wicked;
O Devi, la Tua natura è soggiogare la condotta dei malvagi;
this is Your peerless beauty inconceivable by others;
questa è la Tua impareggiabile bellezza inconcepibile agli altri.
Your power destroys those who have robbed the Devas of their prowess,
Il Tuo potere annienta coloro che hanno derubato i Deva del loro valore
and You have thus manifested Your compassion even towards the enemies.
e Tu hai così manifestato la Tua compassione persino nei confronti dei nemici.
What is Your prowess to be compared to? Where can one find this beauty (of Yours)
A cosa deve essere paragonato il Tuo valore? Dove si può trovare una bellezza
most charming, yet striking fear in enemies?
così incantevole ma che allo stesso tempo terrorizza i nemici?
Compassion in heart and relentlessness in battle are seen, O Devi,
O Devi, o Dispensatrice di grazie, in tutti i tre mondi
O Bestower of boons, only in You in all the three worlds!
si vedono compassione nel cuore e implacabilità in battaglia in Te sola!
Through the destruction of the enemies all the three worlds have been saved by You.
Con la distruzione dei nemici tutti i tre mondi sono stati salvati da Te.
Having killed them in the battlefront, You have led even those hosts of enemies
Avendoli uccisi affrontandoli sul fronte, Tu hai elevato persino
Salutations to You.
Omaggio a Te.
Oh Devi, protect us with Your spear. O Ambika, protect us with Your sword,
O Devi, proteggici con la Tua lancia. O Ambika, proteggici con la Tua spada,
protect us by the sound of Your bell and by the sound of Your bow-string.
proteggici con il suono della Tua campana e della corda del Tuo arco.
O Chandika, guard us in the east, in the west, in the north and in the south
O Chandika, proteggici ad est, ad ovest, a nord e a sud
by the waving of Your spear, O Ishwari!
con la Tua lancia ondeggiante, o Ishwari!
Protect us and the earth with those lovely forms of Yours,
Proteggi noi e la terra muovendoti nei tre mondi con quelle Tue adorabili forme,
O Ambika, protect us on every side with Your sword, spear and club
O Ambika, proteggici da ogni lato con la Tua spada, lancia, mazza
and whatever other weapons Your soft hand has touched. Amen.
ed ogni altra arma toccata dalla Tua mano delicata. Amen.
Pujari and the yogis: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Il pujari e gli yogi: Sakshat Shri Adi Shakti Bhagavati Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji: Very well. All right. Just vibrations are too much.
Shri Mataji: Ottimo. Bene. Le vibrazioni sono proprio troppe.
(Hindi) Havan? Eh? Pujari: ...Aarti...
(Hindi) Havan? Come? Pujari: …Aarti…
Shri Mataji: Aarti. [Hindi conversation with pujari]
Shri Mataji: Aarti (conversazione in hindi con il pujari).
Pujari: Let us sing the Aarti to Shri Mataji now.
Pujari: Cantiamo adesso l’Aarti a Shri Mataji.
Shri Mataji: Don’t play those… which one were you playing yesterday?
Shri Mataji: Non suonate quelli… quali strumenti suonavate ieri?
Which bell were you playing yesterday?
Quali campanelli suonavate ieri?
Yesterday which one was played?
Ieri qual è stato suonato?
Warren: Which one did you use yesterday? It was bad sound.
Warren: Quale avete usato ieri? Aveva un brutto suono.
Yogi: These small brasses. Shri Mataji: These? You know, something else was there.
Yogi: Questi piccoli di ottone. Shri Mataji: Questi? C’era qualcos’altro.
Yogi: Somebody had some different… Shri Mataji: Hm? What’s that?
Yogi: Qualcuno ne aveva alcuni diversi… Shri Mataji: Come? Che cos’è quello?
These you used yesterday? These are all right.
Ieri avete usato questi? Questi vanno bene.
Yesterday something else was here. Yogi: They’re metal, Mother, they’re not brass.
Ieri qui c’era qualcos’altro. Yogi: Sono di metallo, Madre, non di ottone.
Shri Mataji: Let Me see. These are from where? Ah, this is good.
Shri Mataji: Fammi vedere. Da dove arrivano? Ah, questo va bene.
These are from India? Gavin: Some present from India, yes.
Questi arrivano dall’India? Gavin: Qualche regalo dall’India, sì.
They were given to the sahaja yogis in Bombay, I think. Shri Mataji: Who gave?
Sono stati dati ai sahaja yogi a Bombay, penso. Shri Mataji: Chi li ha dati?
Gavin: Somebody in India, I don’t know… Shri Mataji: No, it’s not correct,
Gavin: Qualcuno in India, non lo so … Shri Mataji: No, non va bene,
this is not all right. That’s all right, that’s all right.
questo non va bene. Quello va bene, quello è a posto.
And this you need not play. Only that will do.
Questo non dovete suonarlo. Soltanto l’altro.
For that you have a very big one, which goes with the complete, you see,
Per questo ne avete uno molto grande che va con il completo… vedete,
because the movement –
perché il movimento -
next time they are going to present you with that bell, big bell,
la prossima volta vi regaleranno quella campana, una grande campana,
and the antah gharial (?).
e antah gharial (?).
Such vibrations, I tell you.
Che vibrazioni, vi dico.
Yogi: Sarva Devi Deva Maha Moksha Pradayini Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Yogi: Sarva Devi Deva Maha Moksha Pradayini Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Gli yogi: Jai!
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Mahalakshmi
Mahasaraswati Mahakali
Mahasaraswati Mahakali
Trigunatmika Kundalini Sakshat
Trigunatmika Kundalini Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Adi Shakti Sakshat Shri Bhagavati Sakshat
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Om twameva Sakshat Shri Kalki Sakshat
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji
Shri Sahastrara Swamini Moksha Pradayini Mataji
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Shri Nirmala Devyai Namoh Namah.
Pujari: Bolo Shri Parameshwari Mata Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki!
Pujari: Bolo Shri Parameshwari Mata Shri Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki!
Yogis: Jai!
Gli yogi: Jai!
Yogi: Bolo Shri Mahadevi Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Yogi: Bolo Shri Mahadevi Mataji Shri Nirmala Devi ki! Gli yogi: Jai!
Yogi 2: Nirmala Shakti Mataji
Yogi 2: Nirmala Shakti Mataji
Shri Mataji: Today I bless you specially that you’ll meet all My bhaktas,
Shri Mataji: Oggi vi benedico in modo speciale affinché incontriate
and Sahaja Yoga will grow very fast, all over the world.
e Sahaja Yoga si espanda molto rapidamente in tutto il mondo.
I also bless you, those people who will try to attack you,
Vi benedico anche affinché quanti cercheranno di attaccarvi
will become sahaja yogis.
diventino sahaja yogi.
The highest of all, I bless you with the power of cleansing yourself,
E, soprattutto, vi benedico con il potere di purificare voi stessi
and cleansing others with your love, with your devotion, with your dedication.
e purificare gli altri con il vostro amore, la vostra devozione, la vostra dedizione.
May Adi Shakti bless you then.
Possa dunque l’Adi Shakti benedirvi.
Yogi: Jai Mataji!
Yogi: Jai Mataji!
Gavin: Mataji Nirmala Devi ki! Yogis: Jai!
Gavin: Mataji Nirmala Devi ki! Gli yogi: Jai!
Shri Mataji: May God bless you.
Shri Mataji: Dio vi benedica.
Gavin: Mother, whatever mistakes we’ve made… Shri Mataji: How much time do we have
Gavin: Madre, qualsiasi errore abbiamo commesso… Shri Mataji: Quanto manca
for the lunch? What time did you have lunch?
al pranzo? A che ora avete pranzato (ieri)?
Yogi: Yesterday it was about quarter to one, Mother.
Yogi: Ieri era circa l’una meno un quarto, Madre.
Shri Mataji: Will they do it at one o’clock, if you tell them? So we can finish?
Shri Mataji: Potranno spostarlo all’una, se glielo dici? Così possiamo terminare.
Yogi: It’s normally one o’clock. One o’ clock. Shri Mataji: See?
Yogi: Di solito è all’una. All’una. Shri Mataji: Visto?
Please ask them to keep it one. All right. Or one fifteen,
Per favore, chiedi di fissarlo per l’una. Bene. Oppure l’una e un quarto,
one fifteen would be better. Or one o’ clock. All right.
l’una e un quarto è meglio. Anzi, l’una. Va bene.
Yogi: Mother, he told me quarter to one… Shri Mataji: Hm?
Yogi: Madre, lui mi ha detto l’una meno un quarto… Shri Mataji: Come?
Yogi: …before the puja. Shri Mataji: What’s it?
Yogi: … prima del puja. Shri Mataji: Come?
Yogi: The warden told me quarter to one for the lunch.
Yogi: Il guardiano mi ha detto l’una meno un quarto, per il pranzo.
Warren: Quarter to one. The warden told him a quarter to one,
Warren: L’una meno un quarto. Prima dell’inizio del puja
before starting the puja.
il guardiano gli ha detto all’una meno un quarto.
Shri Mataji: Just request him … Warren: We could change.
Shri Mataji: Chiedigli… Warren: Possiamo cambiare.
Yogi: Let’s just change it, just change it to one o’clock. Yogi 2: One o’ clock, yes.
Yogi: Cambiamo, cambiamo, all’una. Yogi 2: All’una, sì.
Shri Mataji: You see, you say that I went and told they -
Shri Mataji: Vedi, digli che io sono andata a dire…
because it is one o’clock always, so better to have it at one. Let’s go down.
infatti è sempre all’una, quindi è meglio farlo all’una. Scendiamo.
There should be no objection because, for having earlier, you know, people.
Non dovrebbero esserci obiezioni per accogliere prima la gente.
Yogi: No, no, no. Shri Mataji: (Hindi)
Yogi: No, no, no. Shri Mataji: (Hindi)
Is there any arrangement already? Yogi: No. For havan? (Inaudible)
C’è già qualche disposizione? Yogi: No. Per l’havan? (Non udibile)
You know, we don’t actually - in India you don’t get (indistinct).
Sapete, in realtà in India non si trova (non udibile) -
What is this? Is rather particular one.
che cos’è questo? È piuttosto particolare.
Yogi: I think it’s a metal alloy. Shri Mataji: Eh?
Yogi: Penso sia una lega metallica. Shri Mataji: Come?
Yogi: I think it’s a metal alloy… metal alloy - mixture of metals.
Yogi: Penso sia una lega metallica… lega metallica. Una miscela di metalli …
Shri Mataji: Ah, metal… (indistinct words, sentence ends with ‘maryada’ or ‘maryadas’).
Shri Mataji: Ah, metallo… (parole indistinte. La frase termina con ‘maryada’).